Guide to Collection of Italian Prisoner of War and Blue Division Letters TAM.773
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Collection of Italian Prisoner of War and Blue Division Letters
1936-1946
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jackson, Kevin
TAM.773
1.25 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, and 1 half manuscript box.
This collection primarily contains correspondence from Italian prisoners of war during World War II. Various prisoners were at P.O.W. camps in Algeria, Egypt, Kenya, East Africa (E.A.C., East Africa Command), South Africa, Australia, India, Great Britain, India, the United States, Italy, and Germany. Also included are correspondence and papers from a soldier and the chaplain of the Blue Division, a group of Spanish volunteers that served in the Germany Army on the Eastern Front of the Second World War.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Kevin Jackson, February 2015. There is no information regarding the original provenance. The accession number associated with this gift is 2019.010.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor. Letters were received in packets organized by location of POW camp.
Historical Note on Italian Prisoners of War
Following the 1943 Armistice of Cassibile, in which Italy surrendered to the Allies, Germany retaliated and occupied most of Italy to the north, creating a puppet state, the Italian Social Republic. Rather than continue fighting as allies of the German army, the majority of Italian soldiers and officers arrested by Nazi Germany and Italian fascists were taken to German internment camps in Germany or Eastern Europe. Instead of being called prisoners of war, Germany re-designated these detainees as "military internees" as a way to work around the rights granted prisoners of war, as outlined by the Third Geneva Convention.
Even after the armistice, there was no change in status for Italian POWs interned in Allied prisoner of war camps. Due to labor shortages in Great Britain, Australia, and the United States, they were retained as POWs.
Historical Note on the Blue Division
In the Second World War, a group of Spanish volunteers and conscripts served in the German Army, fighting on the Eastern Front. They were called the Blue Division, or División Española de Voluntarios by the Spanish Army, and 250. Infanterie-Division by the German Army.
Scope and Contents
This collection primarily contains correspondence from Italian prisoners of war during World War II. Various prisoners were at P.O.W. camps in Algeria, Egypt, Kenya, East Africa, South Africa, Australia, India, Great Britain, India, the United States, Italy, and Germany. The grouping of East Africa comes from the letters identified as coming out of the East Africa Command (E.A.C.) and/or the Middle East Command, both of which were commands of the Britishy Army.
Also included are correspondence and papers from a soldier and the chaplain of the Blue Division, a group of Spanish volunteers that served in the Germany Army on the Eastern Front of the Second World War.
Prisoners of war; Prisoner-of-war camps; Camp Butner (N.C.); Fort George G. Meade (Md.); World War, 1939-1945.; Correspondence.; Vives, José María; Germany. Heer. Infanteriedivision (1941-1943), 250.
- Ministero dell'Africa Italiana, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- POWs in Algeria, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- POWs in Algeria, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- POWs in Eritrea, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- POWs in the United States, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- POWs in Egypt, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- POWs in Eritrea, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- POWs in South Africa, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- POWs in India, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- POWs in East Africa/Middle East (1 of 2), 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- POWs in East Africa/Middle East (2 of 2), 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- POWs in Italy, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- POWs in Egypt, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- POWs in Australia, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- POWs in India, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- POWs in Kenya, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- POWs in Great Britain, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- POWs in South Africa, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- POWs in Algeria, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- POWs in Egypt, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- POWs in Germany, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- POWs in India, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- POWs in Germany (1 of 2), 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- POWs in Germany (2 of 2), 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Blue Division Soldier's Letters, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Blue Division Chaplain's Letters, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 2)